<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://endaflynn198.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://endaflynn198.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-28T13:45:32+00:00</updated><id>https://endaflynn198.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Shiny App for HDI Indicators</title><link href="https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/HDI_indicators_shiny/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shiny App for HDI Indicators"/><published>2024-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/HDI_indicators_shiny</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/HDI_indicators_shiny/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction-to-shiny">Introduction to Shiny</h1> <p>Shiny is an R package that makes it easy to build interactive web apps straight from R. You can host standalone apps on a webpage or embed them in R Markdown documents, Quarto documents, or build dashboards. You can also extend your Shiny apps with CSS themes, htmlwidgets, and JavaScript actions.</p> <p>There is an excellent <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/r/gallery/">gallery</a> demonstrating the capabilities of Shiny which I highly recommend checking out.</p> <h1 id="the-app">The App</h1> <p>The app is designed to be simple and easy to use, with a clean and modern design.</p> <p>Feel free to check out the code and make modifications for your own Shiny apps. I have also included a video demonstration of the app below so you can see it in action and get a sense of the functionality Shiny provides.</p> <div class="row mt-1"> <div class="col-sm mt-1 mt-md-0"> <video class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" controls=""> <source src="/assets/video/2024-07-26 11-51-20.mkv" type="video/mp4"/> Your browser does not support the video tag. </video> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Note the array of options available to the user in the sidebar, and the use of toggles, lists, and select inputs to make the app more user-friendly and reactive. </div> <h2 id="code">Code</h2> <p>As usual, I have created a <a href="https://github.com/endaflynn198/hdi_shiny_app">GitHub repository</a> for this project. The app is designed to allow the user to select a country and analyse their Human Development Indicators data. The app is built using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shiny</code> package and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HDI_summary</code> package I developed previously.</p> <h1 id="an-issue-with-shiny---samey-aesthetics">An Issue with Shiny - Samey Aesthetics</h1> <p>Shiny has options for theming (the application demonstrated in the video makes use of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sandstone</code> theme from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shinythemes</code>) , but despite this many applications end up looking very similar. You likely noticed this immediately if you visited the gallery.</p> <p>This is because Shiny is built on Bootstrap, which is a very popular CSS framework. This means that many Shiny apps look like Bootstrap apps, which is not a bad thing, but it does mean that they can look a bit generic and outdated.</p> <h2 id="alternatives-for-more-attractive-shiny-apps">Alternatives for More Attractive Shiny Apps</h2> <p>If you want to make your Shiny apps look more modern and unique, you have a few options:</p> <ul> <li> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shiny.fluent</code>: This is a package that provides a fluent design theme for Shiny apps. Fluent design is a design language developed by Microsoft that is used in Windows 10 and other Microsoft products. It is a modern, clean, and attractive design that can make your Shiny apps look more professional.</p> </li> <li> <p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">shiny.semantic</code>: This is a package that provides a semantic UI theme for Shiny apps. Semantic UI is a popular CSS framework that is known for its clean, modern design. It is a good choice if you want to make your Shiny apps look more modern and unique.</p> </li> </ul> <p>There are also other options for theming Shiny apps which are worth exploring, but due to the fact that they add additional dependencies and complexity, I would advise picking one that you like and sticking with it to build familiarity with the syntax and options available.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="code"/><category term="r"/><category term="shiny"/><category term="update"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Shiny App to analyse UN Human Development Indicators]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">R Package for HDI Indicators</title><link href="https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/HDI_indicators/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="R Package for HDI Indicators"/><published>2024-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/HDI_indicators</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/HDI_indicators/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="learning-to-build-an-r-package">Learning to Build an R Package</h1> <p>The last few weeks I’ve learned how to build an R package. While I’ve been using R extensively for a while (almost a decade…), I’ve only built packages in Python before.</p> <p>At the beginning of the process, I was frustrated with some of the quirks of R package building. However, with a bit more experience, I’ve come to see the benefits of helpers like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">devtools</code>,<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">usethis</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">roxygen2</code>.</p> <p>Maybe in future I’ll write a post on how to build an R package from scratch. But for now, I’ve provided <a href="#resources">Resources</a> below which I found useful.</p> <h2 id="the-data---hdi-indicators">The Data - HDI Indicators</h2> <p>The UN Human Development Indicators dataset encompasses a broad range of data that reflect the multi-dimensional aspects of human development across countries. These indicators offer insights into the health, education levels, and economic status of different populations, providing a comprehensive understanding of global human development trends.</p> <p>You can find the data <a href="https://data.humdata.org/dataset/?organization=undp-human-development-reports-office&amp;q=Human+Development+Indicators">here</a>.</p> <h2 id="the-package">The Package</h2> <p>The package I’ve built is designed to allow the easy summary and comparison of UN Human Development Indicators data.</p> <p>While it’s somewhat basic (as it’s more of a learning exercise), it does offer some useful functions for summarising and comparing the data between different countries. And, of course, being an R package it can be easily extended to include more functionality in future.</p> <p>You can install it from GitHub using the following code:</p> <div class="language-r highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="n">devtools</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">install_github</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">"endaflynn198/HDI_summary"</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="n">library</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">HDIsummary</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div> <p>And you can get a sense of the package by reading the vignette comparing Singapore and Nigeria <a href="https://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/endaflynn198/HDI_summary/blob/main/vignettes/HDIsummary.html">here</a>.</p> <blockquote> <p>Note that the above link makes use of GitHub’s HTML previewer which you can find <a href="https://htmlpreview.github.io/">here</a>. I highly recommend it for sharing HTML files in your GitHub repositories as GitHub doesn’t render them directly.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="resources">Resources</h2> <p>If you’re interested in learning more about building R packages, I recommend the following resources:</p> <ol> <li><a href="https://r-pkgs.org/">R Packages by Hadley Wickham and Jennifer Bryan</a></li> <li><a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/rstudio/cheatsheets/main/package-development.pdf">RStudio’s Package Development Cheat Sheet</a></li> </ol> <h2 id="soundtrack">Soundtrack</h2> <p>While building this package I’ve been listening to a lot of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0N0QVRWWt6g">The Four Freshmen</a> - a harmonic highlight of an old favourite is at 3.10 of the linked video. Soothing when you’re trying to figure out why your package isn’t building properly or restarting your R session for the 10th time…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="code"/><category term="r"/><category term="package"/><category term="update"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new R package for analysing UN Human Development Indicators]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Website Update</title><link href="https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Website Update"/><published>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://endaflynn198.github.io/blog/2024/update/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="website-update">Website Update</h1> <p>As I’ve been updating this website in my downtime, things have been moving slowly but surely. The last while I’ve added / changed the following:</p> <ol> <li>Updated the home page to include a brief bio</li> <li>Updated the CV page and added a link to a (mostly) updated PDF version</li> <li>Added my two GitHub repositories</li> <li>Removed the template news items</li> </ol> <p>There’s still a lot to do, but I’m happy with the progress so far and I’m looking forward to adding more content and features in the future. Some of these will take a bit more work - adding more of my projects to GitHub and presenting this in the projects tab, for example - but it’s all part of the fun in learning how to use Jekyll and GitHub Pages.</p> <p>I’m also looking forward to adding substantive blog posts over the next while (and removing the template blog posts). I’ve been working on a few projects in my spare time that I’m excited to share, so stay tuned for that.</p> <p>Within the next few weeks (or months) I’ll have a more polished website to show off. Until then, thanks for stopping by!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="website-update"/><category term="update"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[an update on the website progress]]></summary></entry></feed>